<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Coding Mantis</title><link href="http://abstatic.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://abstatic.github.io/feeds/configuration.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://abstatic.github.io/</id><updated>2016-07-01T01:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>i3 Window Manager FTW</title><link href="http://abstatic.github.io/how-i-use-i3wm.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-01T01:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava  &lt;x.abhishek.flyhigh@gmail.com&gt;</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2016-07-01:how-i-use-i3wm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Tiling Window What&amp;nbsp;?!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Window Manager&lt;/strong&gt; - Okay, lets clear the most basic thing first, a window
manager is the program which generally draws the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt; of your computer. Most of
the time the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WM&lt;/span&gt; is not just one program, but a suite of programs designed to
fulfill most of the daily requirements of the&amp;nbsp;users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNOME&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt;, Unity,&amp;nbsp;Mate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tiling Window&amp;nbsp;Managers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WMs like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GNOME&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KDE&lt;/span&gt;, Unity, Mate etc are what we call floating window
managers, these are the types of window managers in which the windows are
floating are draggable, resizeable, overlapping and all the frilly&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tiling window managers are a special class of window managers, where windows
fit in the display just like tiles. The screen is organized into mutually
non-overlapping&amp;nbsp;frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rough idea of how tiling window managers look like&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="i3-screen" src="https://i3wm.org/screenshots/i3-9.bigthumb.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="i3-screen2" src="http://i3wm.org/screenshots/i3-6.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In tiling window managers you cannot just drag windows and stuff. Its very
different from the usual desktop&amp;nbsp;managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest I was never a fan of tiling window managers, but one day out of
the blue I decided to give tiling window managers a try. Thus began endless
googling about which tiling window manager should I use ? , and I setteledd
for&amp;nbsp;i3wm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the conditions I had in my mind when evaluating various wms&amp;#8217;
and how i3wm is fulfulling all of these&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There should be ample and &lt;strong&gt;easy to understand documentation&lt;/strong&gt; - i3 has
   excellent documentation, infact having ample and understandable
   documentation is one of the design philosophies of this&amp;nbsp;wm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuration should be simple&lt;/strong&gt;, as I did not want to learn another
   scripting language, just to configure my window manager - Configuration is
   done using plaintext configuration files using human readable language,&amp;nbsp;keywords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy installation&lt;/strong&gt;, it should not result in any downtime of my&amp;nbsp;machine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i3wm package is available for almost all of the distros, and its strctly
     a wm, no extra package is installed, only one kickass window&amp;nbsp;manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good tutorials, and user base&lt;/strong&gt; - Tons of information on reddit, forums and
   youtube tutorials are&amp;nbsp;available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excellent support for multiple monitors&lt;/strong&gt; - Most screen efficient&amp;nbsp;display.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support for good keybindings, hence minimizing the use for mouse - &lt;strong&gt;Has vim
   like keybindings&lt;/strong&gt; What else can I want more&amp;nbsp;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a overview of how I am using i3wm, here is what my screens look
like - (&lt;a href="http://abstatic.github.io/my-current-configuration.html"&gt;I use triple
displays&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="My current screens" src="http://i.imgur.com/K1stHJt.png" title="Open image in a new tab to see zoomed in" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blank space is because two of my screens are set to 1366x768 px and one is
set to 1920x1080px, but that&amp;#8217;s not the&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some official videos about i3wm and the containers and tree data
strucutres it uses&amp;nbsp;- &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wx0eNaGzAZU"&gt;i3 Basics&lt;/a&gt; - This video covers the bare basics of i3wm and various modes
Before we get out hands dirty with 
  it&amp;nbsp;supports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AWA8Pl57UBY"&gt;Containers and tree data structure of
  i3&lt;/a&gt; - Great video which covers how
  the windows are handled in i3 using tree data structure. Must watch if you
  want to understand how to manipulate containers and other&amp;nbsp;stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;i3 Conf&lt;/strong&gt; - Out of the box, i3 is okay-ish. But with the right configuration
this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WM&lt;/span&gt; becomes very&amp;nbsp;powerful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my i3 &lt;a href="https://github.com/abstatic/config/blob/master/i3conf/config"&gt;conf file&lt;/a&gt; 
The default location for this file is &lt;code&gt;~/.i3/config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first screen has one vertical container and two horizontally tiled&amp;nbsp;containers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second screen has only one program open,&amp;nbsp;vim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third screen has tabbed layout,  with multiple tabs&amp;nbsp;open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dmenu&lt;/strong&gt; - dmenu is the built in i3 launcher. Its activated my pressing &lt;code&gt;$mod
+ d&lt;/code&gt; , and is used for launching various applications and stuff. You can also
  use other launchers. I find dmenu to be sufficient and use it most of the
  time. You might want to check out rofi, its an excellent alternative and is
  feature&amp;nbsp;filled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;i3bar&lt;/strong&gt; - The bar at the bottom of each screen is i3bar, its a simple
program which shows the output of either the inbuilt or third party program.
It shows the system status and other&amp;nbsp;things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use py3status for outputting the status. You can install py3status using pip
or your distributions package&amp;nbsp;manager. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The status line is configured using the i3status.conf file. Here is my 
configuration
&lt;a href="https://github.com/abstatic/config/blob/master/i3conf/i3status.conf"&gt;file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marks&lt;/strong&gt; - Marks allow you to mark a window and then you can easily do a goto
on that mark from any random window that you are&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keybindings&lt;/strong&gt; - I have kept the keybingds similar to that of vim. Its very
handy and easy to&amp;nbsp;remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Managing Audio, Networks and other&amp;nbsp;stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing audio and networks can be cumbersome from the terminal. For this 
I use two excellent programs&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nm-applet - Used for managing the wireless&amp;nbsp;networks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pavucontrol - Pulse audio volume control, this software is really great and
   allows to manage your audio and card from a nice &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I manually execute &lt;code&gt;pavucontrol&lt;/code&gt; , I have added &lt;code&gt;nm-applet&lt;/code&gt; to the
startup&amp;nbsp;entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;exec nm-applet&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;File manager&lt;/strong&gt; - Its unwise to file managers like Files (Gnome) or
Nautilus(Ubuntu) on i3, as they try to manage your desktop as well. I use
pcman file manager as my file manager. Its extremely lightweigt and does the&amp;nbsp;job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GTk themes&lt;/strong&gt; - Install &lt;code&gt;lxappearance&lt;/code&gt; , if you want to tinker with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GTK&lt;/span&gt;
themes and&amp;nbsp;stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VLC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - This is one my favourite tasks, you can fill applications like &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VLC&lt;/span&gt;,
and other players in the containers. To do this, first go to full screen, and
then press &lt;code&gt;$MOD + F&lt;/code&gt;, the program will now fill the container in which it is&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjusting sound and brightness&lt;/strong&gt; - I use custom keyboard shortcuts for
changing sound and&amp;nbsp;brightness.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Using multiple&amp;nbsp;monitors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i3wm is great for people using multiple monitors. It detects all the connected
displays right of the box. There is no extra program to manage your monitors,
so you have to learn to configure xrandr options to make full use of your
multiple&amp;nbsp;monitors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By having to configure xrandr, it becomes a good learning exercise as&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one command that I execute with every startup&amp;nbsp;- &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;exec --no-startup-id xrandr --output HDMI1 --left-of eDP1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[My multiple monitor setup]&amp;nbsp;(http://abstatic.github.io/my-current-configuration.html)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing&amp;nbsp;wallpapers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use nitrogen for for managing wallpapers on my different displays. Its&amp;nbsp;awesome. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;exec --no-startup-id nitrogen --restore&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now my experience with i3wm has been awesome. Its minamilist nature is
really good. You get all of the screen space to yourself and can utilize it
any way you&amp;nbsp;want.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Linux"></category><category term="configuration"></category><category term="i3"></category><category term="i3window manager"></category><category term="i3wm"></category><category term="developer configuration"></category></entry><entry><title>My Configuration</title><link href="http://abstatic.github.io/my-current-configuration.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-07-01T01:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava  &lt;x.abhishek.flyhigh@gmail.com&gt;</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2016-07-01:my-current-configuration.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Okay, so this blog post is about my current computer configuration that I use
for day to day development. This post will cover each and everything related
to my developer configuration. Right from the mouse and keyboard to the
intracies of i3wm, the tiling window manager that I use&amp;nbsp;;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my old setup&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="old setup" src="http://i.imgur.com/xc43jrq.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and here is &amp;#8220;The&amp;#8221; Setup, my laptop remained same though :P&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="new setup" src="http://i.imgur.com/l5bUH95.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powering all of my day to day tasks is my &lt;a href="http://www.flipkart.com/acer-aspire-e5-e5-573-587q-core-i5-4th-gen-4-gb-1-tb-hdd-linux-128-mb-graphics-notebook-nx-mvhsi-068/p/itmecq2b72uhje8d"&gt;acer&amp;nbsp;laptop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its an entry level laptop with a good processor. The configuration is as
follows&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processor - Intel Core i5 - 4th Generation, 1.7Ghz -&amp;nbsp;2.7Ghz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RAM&lt;/span&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;4GB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DDR3&lt;/span&gt; Memory (which, soon will be upgraded to&amp;nbsp;8gigs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDD&lt;/span&gt; - &lt;span class="caps"&gt;1TB&lt;/span&gt; (Pretty standard these&amp;nbsp;days)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphics - Intel &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HD&lt;/span&gt; 4400 (with 2048mb, can play dota2 at 40fps normal&amp;nbsp;settings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part about this laptop is the graphics card, honestly. It has
 separte slots for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VGA&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDMI&lt;/span&gt;. If you connect two separate outputs to these
 you get an extended display of three monitors (including the&amp;nbsp;laptop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It works flawlessly, and this is the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USP&lt;/span&gt; of this laptop for&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keyboard, Mouse and&amp;nbsp;Audio&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been using Dragonwar Q2 set of keyboard and mouse for quite some time&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard&lt;/strong&gt; - The keyboard is semi mechanical with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; lights, which is the
central feature for me, as I spend a lot of time coding in the&amp;nbsp;night. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cable is braided kevlar which is of very high quality and is more than
sufficient in length. The only downside of this keyboard is that its
multimedia keys are not supported in linux, and sadly there is no fix for
this. (What, a&amp;nbsp;sham)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backlight is color can be changed as well or turned of&amp;nbsp;entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="keyboard" src="http://i.imgur.com/fXlywFL.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typing is a breeze in this keyboard, and it feels effortlesss to press the&amp;nbsp;keys. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mouse&lt;/strong&gt; - The mouse model is &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GKM&lt;/span&gt;-001. It is a pretty cool and the major
features that I found are the extra buttons and the capability to change the
dpi. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; eyecandy doesn&amp;#8217;t hurt as&amp;nbsp;well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mouse" src="http://i.imgur.com/acK8Ra1.jpg" title="Not a GoT fan, it was a gift :)" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently I use my mouse at 3200 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DPI&lt;/span&gt;. Yes, its really sensitive. But then again you
need a sensitive mouse, in order to navigate three displays. At &lt;span class="caps"&gt;3200DPI&lt;/span&gt; I can
traverse through all the three displays by moving my mouse only a few&amp;nbsp;centimeters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio&lt;/strong&gt; - I use my &lt;a href="http://www.mi.com/in/headphones_basic2/"&gt;Mi Earphones&lt;/a&gt;
for all of my audio needs. They are awesome and best bargain for their price 
range. Also include an inbuilt microphone and are compatible with all&amp;nbsp;phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Displays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired from &lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/three-monitors-for-every-user/"&gt;Jeff
Atwood&lt;/a&gt; I have
recently shifted to using triple&amp;nbsp;displays. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tell you, once you start working with multiple displays, there is no turning
back. At&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/000740.html"&gt;Joining the prestigious Three Monitor&amp;nbsp;Club:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Page: I have a weird setup in my office. I have one computer with three
monitors: one flat-screen monitor and two regular ones. I have my browser on
one screen, my schedule on another and my e-mail on another. I can drag things
to different screens. I also have a projector. So if I&amp;#8217;m talking with everyone
in my office, I can move stuff onto a big&amp;nbsp;screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill Gates: If you look at this office, there isn&amp;#8217;t much paper in it. On my
desk I have three screens, synchronized to form a single desktop. I can drag
items from one screen to the next. Once you have that large display area,
you&amp;#8217;ll never go back, because it has a direct impact on&amp;nbsp;productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use triple monitors for maximum&amp;nbsp;productivity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output 1 : Dell &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HD&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LED&lt;/span&gt; @ 1920 x 1080 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FHD&lt;/span&gt; (On &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HDMI&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
Output 2 : Laptop Display @ 1366 x 768&lt;br /&gt;
Output 3 : &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AOC&lt;/span&gt; E970Sw @ 1366 x 768 (On &lt;span class="caps"&gt;VGA&lt;/span&gt;)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="working" src="http://i.imgur.com/savUlZy.jpg" title="Why would I ever want to get up from my chair ?" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell me, why would I ever want to get up from my chair again&amp;nbsp;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every programmer must try these high resolution monitors, the amount of
content that you see on a 1080p monitor is crazy. Every thing looks so big and
you can see so much of the content at one time, mindboggling.  The clarity and
the colors are&amp;nbsp;unparalleled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I am using Ubuntu 14.04 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LTS&lt;/span&gt; dual booted with windows 10 for quite
some time. Both of these will be replaced by either Fedora or Arch and windows 7
after I am done with my gsoc&amp;nbsp;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use i3wm for my window&amp;nbsp;management.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Linux"></category><category term="configuration"></category><category term="dragonwar"></category><category term="i3"></category><category term="i3window manager"></category><category term="i3wm"></category><category term="developer configuration"></category></entry></feed>