<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Coding Mantis - Life</title><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/feeds/life.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://abstatic.github.io/</id><updated>2016-03-01T02:03:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Learning A New Language</title><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/2016/03/01/learning-german/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-03-01T02:03:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-03-01T02:03:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2016-03-01:/2016/03/01/learning-german/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Short Post About How Learning A New Language Opens Up New&amp;nbsp;Frontiers&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been trying to learn German for quite some time, on and off again,
using all the online tools available at my disposal. To be honest, learning
a new language is hard. Especially&amp;nbsp;German. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have observed that with learning a new language we open up a lot of new
frontiers. When learning a language we don&amp;#8217;t learn only the &amp;#8220;language&amp;#8221;,
instead we learn about the society, the heirarchy in society, the culture, the
music and the litereature. I feel this is a priceless&amp;nbsp;bargain.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can learn a lot about a society, its culture by learning the language it
speaks. German as a language has a rich cultural and musical heritage. And it
shows. In the language and the society&amp;nbsp;itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover when we learn a new language, we also open up new possibilities in
music and literature. I have been listening to German music for some hours now
and I find it so calming and beautiful, even though I don&amp;#8217;t understand most of
it.&amp;nbsp;xD&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Life"></category><category term="German"></category></entry><entry><title>Do you love yourself ?</title><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/2014/03/05/do-you-love-yourself/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-05T15:01:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-03-05T15:01:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2014-03-05:/2014/03/05/do-you-love-yourself/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Feeling&amp;nbsp;philosophical&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;10:16pm&lt;/em&gt; This entry a little philosophical but its really close to my
heart and thinking. Its adapted from &amp;#8220;The Speaking Tree&amp;#8221;. With a few
additions here and there from my&amp;nbsp;side.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People feel lonely; they need somebody to fill their loneliness. They
call it love. They show love because that is the only way to hook the
other. the other also calls ot love because that the only way to hook
you. but who knows whether there is love or not ? Love is just a game.
Real love is possible, but that happens only when you don&amp;#8217;t need&amp;nbsp;anybody!  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go to a bank and you need money, they will not give you any. If
you don&amp;#8217;t need money, you have enough, they will come to you and they
will always be ready to give you. Same is the case with love,&amp;nbsp;guys.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you don&amp;#8217;t need a person at all, when you are totally sufficient
unto yourself, when you can be alone and tremendously happy and
ecstatic, then love is possible. But then too you can be certain about
only one thing: whether your love is real. How can you be certain about
the other ? But then there is no&amp;nbsp;need.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This continuous anxiety - whether the other&amp;#8217;s love is real or not-
simply shows one thing: that your love is not real. Why be worried about
it ? Enjoy it while it lasts! Be together while you can be together! It
is a fiction, but you need fiction, right&amp;nbsp;?   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behind declarations of love there is nothing but need. You want your
lover to be with you to fill you emptiness and so too is the case with
her. You are both trying to use each other as a&amp;nbsp;means.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s why lovers, so-called lovers, are always in conflict - because
nobody wants to be used, because when you use a person the person
becomes a thing, you have reduced him to a&amp;nbsp;commodity.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you love yourself ? You have not even asked the question. When you
are really blissful on your own, you don&amp;#8217;t want to use anybody. You
simply want to share it. And you will feel thankful that somebody was
ready to receive, not to take. That is the full&amp;nbsp;point.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no way to be certain about the other- first be ceratin about
yourself. And a person who is certain about himself is ceratin about the
whole world. Settled, centred, grounded in yourself, you never worry
about such things. You&amp;nbsp;accept.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If somebody loves you, you accept it because you love yourself. You are
happy with yourself; somebody else is happy- good ! While it lasts, live
the fiction as beautifully as possible- it will not last forever.
Nothing lasts&amp;nbsp;forever.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a love is finished, you start thinking it was false- that&amp;#8217;s why it
has come to an end. No, not necessarily. It may have had some glimmer of
truth in it, but you were not capable of&amp;nbsp;it.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are aware, a totally different kind of love wil arise in your
heart- which is absolutely true, which is part of eternity. But that is
not need- it is a luxury. And you have so much of it that you hanker for
somebody to share it&amp;nbsp;with.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="MyLife"></category></entry><entry><title>Chronosphere.</title><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/2014/02/25/chronosphere/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-25T16:31:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-02-25T16:31:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava (xabhishekflyhigh@gmail.com)</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2014-02-25:/2014/02/25/chronosphere/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;"&gt;

I wrote this poem in my last week in Kota. Shit. I&amp;#8217;ve come a really long
way from back then.  

Chronosphere is a place in space where everything seems to have stopped,
even time. So, here it goes.  

As I sit here, watching the hands tick by,  
Listening to …&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div dir="ltr" style="text-align: left;"&gt;

I wrote this poem in my last week in Kota. Shit. I&amp;#8217;ve come a really long
way from back then.  

Chronosphere is a place in space where everything seems to have stopped,
even time. So, here it goes.  

As I sit here, watching the hands tick by,  
Listening to the birds, fill up the sky.  
Thoughts floating round my head,  
ricking back and forth in my bed.  
Emotions are rising, clouding my heart  
Yet another day, How on earth do I start ?  
The tears well up, but still never fall,  
I wish, I wish I was strong enought to end this all. :(  

As my mind monsters catch up, my heart fills with dread  
Why couldn&amp;#8217;t I be someone else instead ?!  
Someone with a passion for this life we &amp;#8220;live&amp;#8221;  
Someone more than just hate to give.  

I try to think of How I got here.  
I tread a troubled track. My odds are stacked.  
How have I reached such a horrible place ?  
Where everything is just to scary to face.  
Is it just that I&amp;#8217;m not born to this life ?  

Confusion, pain &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; sadness fill my heart.  
Maybe today-I hope- I&amp;#8217;ll bring me my new fresh start.  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="MyLife"></category></entry><entry><title>A Long time…perhaps ?</title><link href="https://abstatic.github.io/2014/02/25/a-long-time-perhaps/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-02-25T16:18:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-02-25T16:18:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Abhishek Shrivastava</name></author><id>tag:abstatic.github.io,2014-02-25:/2014/02/25/a-long-time-perhaps/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Outburst after realizing how shitty my college&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So finally I can allow myself the luxury of blogging&amp;#8230;Well, college life is demanding. These blasted profs , kuch kehna hi bekar hai and my
fellow branch mates ! , Believe it or not one guy in my class thinks that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt; is an input device!! Just wanted to shoot myself then -_-
, and the most irritating thing about all of them is that they think
Windows is better than Linux , &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WAKE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UP&lt;/span&gt; from your slumber guys otherwise
just be windows using minions for all I care &gt;.\&amp;lt; . I mean &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CS&lt;/span&gt; majors
are supposed to be a class apart, smarter than everyone in the room.
&amp;#8230;..But anyways I do hope to find someone as interested as me in&amp;nbsp;computers.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the college campus and infrastructure is nice , wi-fi and a working
leaseline connection and a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LAN&lt;/span&gt; network of more than 200-300 computers.
&lt;strong&gt;Edit: Shittiest college ever. Nothing&amp;nbsp;works.&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest downside of coming to Bhopal in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UIT&lt;/span&gt; so far is I&amp;#8217;ve
completely forgotten &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JS&lt;/span&gt;, which is really sad :( , and it all
happened due to using Sublime Text. Infact from now on I will be using
GVim even though the learning curve is really steep but at least I will
remember the syntax then and Vi is way more powerful than any of the
text editors around and its the only text editor around with a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CLI&lt;/span&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PS&lt;/span&gt;:- The next entry is not gonna be so melodramatic , its gonna be about
Auto &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FS&lt;/span&gt; mounting in&amp;nbsp;Linux.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="MyLife"></category></entry></feed>